<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog Name</title>
  <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
  <id>http://blog.url.com/</id>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/"/>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2015-03-24T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Postgres with Rails on Linux Mint</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2015/03/24/postgres-for-rails-in-linux.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2015/03/24/postgres-for-rails-in-linux.html</id>
    <published>2015-03-24T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2015-11-18T17:56:46+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;article&gt;
  &lt;h1&gt;Postgres with Rails on Linux Mint&lt;/h1&gt;
  &lt;section&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This will be very short to let you know how to set up PostgreSQL so you won't have to use a password. Obviously this isn't the most secure, but this is assuming you don't have sensitive data in your development and test environment. (Which you shouldn't have.)&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;There is an excellent guide on how to set up Postgres on Ubuntu. I use Linux Mint, but 95% of the time an Unbuntu how-to will work on Linux Mint every time. If you haven't done that yet, go do that first:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/PostgreSQL"&gt;Install PostgreSQL on Unbuntu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
  &lt;section&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Minimal configuration&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So what I want for my Rails projects is a postgresql setup which will create the databases I need and be compatible with people I work on projects with who probably use a Mac.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is what my database.yml file would look like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;pre class="highlight ruby"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;#x000A;&lt;span class="ss"&gt;default: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;default&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#x000A;  &lt;span class="ss"&gt;adapter: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;postgresql&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#x000A;  &lt;span class="ss"&gt;encoding: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;unicode&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#x000A;  &lt;span class="ss"&gt;pool: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#x000A;&amp;#x000A;&lt;span class="ss"&gt;development:&amp;#x000A;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;default&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#x000A;  &lt;span class="ss"&gt;database: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;project_name_development&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#x000A;&amp;#x000A;&lt;span class="ss"&gt;test:&amp;#x000A;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;default&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#x000A;  &lt;span class="ss"&gt;database: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;project_name_test&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#x000A;&amp;#x000A;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now with Postgres installed and the configuration set up there was one thing that kept bugging me and it took me some Google searches, visits to StackOverflow and some trial and error before I got it right. So here it is:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
  &lt;section&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;The point of this post&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is where you should go: &lt;span class='inline-code'&gt;/etc/postgresql/9.3/main/pg_hba.conf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then I simply added this line:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;pre class="highlight plaintext"&gt;&lt;code&gt;# TYPE  DATABASE     USER          ADDRESS            METHOD&amp;#x000A;host    all          richard       127.0.0.1/32       trust&amp;#x000A;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This means that for user 'richard' I set a blank password and now allow all connections which I run from Rails. That's it really. Nice and easy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/article&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Web Development, my vocation</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2015/03/12/web-development-my-vocation.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2015/03/12/web-development-my-vocation.html</id>
    <published>2015-03-12T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2015-11-18T17:56:46+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;article&gt;
  &lt;header&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Web Development, my vocation&lt;/h1&gt;
  &lt;/header&gt;
  &lt;section&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I thought about first post on my new blog site. It should be about the technology I used to build it and that will come, but first I wanted to share my motivation as to why I wanted to maintain a blog site in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This blog is an expression of who I am. I am a web developer. This is only a small part of who I am, but strangely enough, it is what I feel very much at home with right now.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
  &lt;section&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Vocation&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Vocation is a powerful word to me. It is something which resonates strongly with my core values, my interests. It is not a job, not a career. A vocation is more powerful than that. More &lt;i&gt;real&lt;/i&gt;. An extension of who I am, going out in the world and contributing what I have to give.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That sounds pretty deep and honestly, I always thought of my vocation being more romantic than web development somehow. Like building a school in Vietnam or Cambodia. Not too long ago, when I still didn't know what I wanted to do when I'd grow up, I actually did things similar to that. While I found it valuable, it wasn't enough for me.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;So I looked into other things I enjoyed and I liked the idea of being able to say I was doing something really cool for a living, like being SCUBA diving or snowboarding instructor. Those are things I came close to or deeply considered. I still love these things, yet it is not something I can pour myself into entirely. Probably for a year or two, but not much longer than that.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
  &lt;section&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Happiness&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I understand happiness is not a constant state of joy, but really a deeper, more low key satisfaction pervading all aspects of life. Maybe it's the same as satisfaction. Being a web developer is only a part of that, but I feel I am now into a profession which suits my interests entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If at this point you are still reading, but don't know too much about web development, I will try to convey what I enjoy about it. First of all, it is exciting to be able to work with edge technology and forward thinking people. To be able to have an idea and make it real and accessible for others. Working with new technologies means there are always problems to solve. In management terms those would be called challenges. I like to think of those as puzzles to crack.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I think writing code and seeing things happen is magical, no matter how logical the explanation is. Figuring out how things work, what things are made of has always been fascinating to me. This is why web development suits me so well. what's more is that technology doesn't just come to a stop. I have a life long of learning ahead of me and I love that idea.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
  &lt;section&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;This blog&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While I felt the need to introduce my motivation for this blog, I think it will mainly focus on the technology I use and try out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I think it's a great way of contributing to the technical community. Personally I remember the number of times a great blog post helped me solve a technical issue I encountered, providing me with concise wording and clear examples. It is my goal to return that favor as often as I have the chance.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/article&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Asking Questions</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2014/10/01/asking-questions.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2014/10/01/asking-questions.html</id>
    <published>2014-10-01T02:00:00+02:00</published>
    <updated>2015-11-18T17:56:46+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;article&gt;
  &lt;header&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;The Art of Asking Questions&lt;/h1&gt;
  &lt;/header&gt;
  &lt;section&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;The right question&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Asking a good question does take more consideration than you would initially think. I have worked in various IT support roles where I had to both answer questions as well ask questions to other specialists. I know what it's like for both sides of the question. It is important to provide brief, yet detailed and only relevant information, while making sure you aren't omitting anything helpful. It can be important to provide environment variables when they are relevant, but they should be very succinct.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When it comes to asking questions about code, I understand it is important to reduce the amount of example code to a minimum and use easy to understand, general variables and names. This is what I took away from the presented article.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Considering my own questions I know I have not actually done that. So far though my questions on code in G+ have been specific to the shared exercises, so we all know the circumstances, but I should keep this in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I ask my questions I definitely position myself as a potential answerer. Sometimes I find the answer to my question by simply writing it out, noticing a detail I haven't tried yet, then try different things on that which will lead me to more useful information if not a complete solution.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;

  &lt;section&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Asking in person&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I approached colleagues with questions I always made sure I had all information ready, either jotted down on paper or by bringing a laptop or making sure we can look at the same screen quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What is emphasized is that the person providing help is taking out time and that is very true. It is goodwill and I make sure to let the other person know it is appreciated. Likewise, I am always happy to help someone who is prepared and whom I know will be helped on their with the provided information. I just believe that we can pass on what we are given. I think that is our natural inclination and I like to accommodate that.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;

&lt;/article&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Site Evaluation</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2014/09/30/site-evaluation.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2014/09/30/site-evaluation.html</id>
    <published>2014-09-30T02:00:00+02:00</published>
    <updated>2015-11-18T17:56:46+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;article&gt;
  &lt;header&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Site Evaluation&lt;/h1&gt;
  &lt;/header&gt;

  &lt;section&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Nine weeks of blogging&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the things DBC taught me is to get into the habit of blogging regularly. While the topics weren't something I would choose to blog about this process has been educative to me. In the cultural blog assignments I considered things I had not considered before. In the technical blogging I realized how blogging really helps solidify the topics I chose.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;I have to admit that when I blogged I always picked the topic I felt most unfamiliar with, so I had to learn about it before and while I blogged about it. This is an efficient way of both increasing and sharing my knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
    

    &lt;p&gt;When I blog the first thing I will consider if it is worthwhile for someone else to read. I hope this has been the case so far and when picking my next blog topics this will be my primary consideration.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;

  &lt;section&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Achievement Unlocked&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I started building my site I had wireframes, but when building it, the wireframes became nothing more but a very rough outline and were soon after forgotten. Looking back at my site now I am happy with the starting page, but I would like to redo my blog page.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;One of the first things I wanted to do once I had my landing page was for it to transition smoothly into the next pages. Being introduced to JQuery allowed me to do just that.

    &lt;p&gt;I did look into using my own domain name on the GitHub pages and I was surprised by how fast I got that done. I expected some more technical hiccups here, but sometime things just go smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;While I didn't get into Jekyll or Middleman yet, I will look into this after DBC as I can see the benefits of using this to generate my templates. It will make it easier to transition to other layouts or fix something without having to go through all my blog posts again.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;I did rethink my blog index page and it makes more sense to me now. It is still a work in progress and I have some ideas on how to improve this. Again, I will take this on after I finish my nine weeks in DBC.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/article&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Conflict</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2014/09/28/conflict.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2014/09/28/conflict.html</id>
    <published>2014-09-28T02:00:00+02:00</published>
    <updated>2015-11-18T17:56:46+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;article&gt;
  &lt;header&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Conflict&lt;/h1&gt;
  &lt;/header&gt;
  &lt;section&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I would like to invite you to do an &lt;a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=conflict&amp;biw=1920&amp;bih=968&amp;source=lnms&amp;tbm=isch&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=ZM4qVJ2EFsjCPIz3gcAL&amp;ved=0CAYQ_AUoAQ"&gt;image search on Google&lt;/a&gt; for conflict. There are two things that I noticed: Almost all of them feature people in traditional office wear and exactly all of them look ridiculous. The only exception is the image with the children being angry with each other. When it comes children it's easy to understand conflict over small things. We all have to learn how to deal with different people and situations. It's when you see adults behave in this way that it is obvious they haven't had the opportunity or wisdom to develop in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am glad to see DBC embracing emotional intelligence where it is made clear we can be angry or annoyed, but don't have to be driven by these emotions. I loved Sharif's talk on the compass of shame, as he indicated that each of these reactions only come forth out of a desire to be of benefit, and that each of these methods are also signs of a unique strength.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
  
  &lt;section&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;My experience&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Discuss a time you had an emotional conflict with someone. What was it about? What happened?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What was the source of the conflict?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;How did you handle that conflict?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Did your actions make the conflict better or worse?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If you could go back, what would you do differently, if anything?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What did you learn from this experience?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;This question makes me realize how lucky I am. I had to think long for a bit on this. I mean, I know I've had a discussions over the taxi price somewhere in South East Asia and I probably expressed my annoyance in some way. It doesn't really matter. Even at those times I don't look at making a stand, but how to solve the situation. And while I can have inner turmoil, it only results in conflict if I believe my frustration or annoyance needs to be directed at a person. I don't believe that anymore. Someone can stand in front of me and yell in my face and I wouldn't call it conflict. Sure, I would experience a range of emotions, maybe fear, guilt, hatred, anger, but in that range of emotions I always have a choice in how to respond. This is what was talked about in the DBC recommended emotional intelligence talks. This is not a new concept to me.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Other than that there are conflicts in my past where I know my actions made things worse through blaming someone or by trying to avoid a person or situation. This was all very painful and while avoidance can seem to remove conflict, it only suppresses it. It always only made things worse.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;If I could go back I would use the wisdom I have now and be more empathetic in the way that I can see the other persons motives are to want the best for me. Their concern for me can be expressed in ineffective ways, but that doesn't mean I have to respond ineffectively.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;I would listen openly, without putting up a defensive stand or preparing a counterattack, making sure the other person is heard and let them know they are heard. Offering resolution where possible, but simply accepting the other persons feelings if resolution cannot be found at that time.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;One way to avoid conflict is by giving in, but again, the conflict simmers on. Just because there isn't a clash does not mean there is no conflict. Only a peaceful allowing of things as they are can resolve conflict naturally. I strongly believe this and have experienced this in my life on several occasions.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;This is why I say I haven't really had any conflict for some time now. And the more I practice lettings things be as they are, the more confident I become in that.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;We cannot really choose our thoughts and emotions, but we can always choose what to do with them. This is where our responsibility lies. This is where the choice lies between being a victim and being free.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;I have to give credit to Balanced View here as the support provided in this grassroots movement has been invaluable to me. Growing up, being out in the world, I always knew there had to be a better way of living than what most people were doing. In the simple practice of lettings things be for short moments I found how. This is what I take with me always, this is how I recognize my emotions stir and my opportunity to make my decisions based on what serves everyone best. I don't take things so personal anymore. This relaxes me and my reactions. In this way conflict cannot really take hold.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/article&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Apache</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2014/09/28/apache.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2014/09/28/apache.html</id>
    <published>2014-09-28T02:00:00+02:00</published>
    <updated>2015-12-13T16:14:07+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;article&gt;
  &lt;header&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Apache Webserver&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;img src="images/blog/nginx_vs_apache.png" /&gt;
    &lt;span class="subtext"&gt;This could also be a beautiful friendship in the making.&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/header&gt;
  &lt;section&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This week I decided to write something about Apache Webserver which is an open source web server and the one most used one in the world. The &lt;a href="http://news.netcraft.com/archives/2014/09/24/september-2014-web-server-survey.html" target="_blank"&gt;latest survey&lt;/a&gt; shows 39.74% of all web servers is Apache. Time for a quick overview.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
  
  &lt;section&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;What is Apache?&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first thing to be aware of that the web server isn't a physical machine like what you would normally think of as a server. Think of it more in the literal sense of the word: It mostly serves web pages, but web pages are simply html files. So a web server can serve any file. The file served depends on several things; The incoming request (person clicking on a link) and the rules set in the web server configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
  &lt;section&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;How does Apache work?&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apache is started through the httpd, the "d" stands for &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daemon_(computing)" target="_blank"&gt;daemon&lt;/a&gt;. Like many terms in IT this is a cool name for a background process. If you are looking for an Apache HTTP server process that would be a good starting point to &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grep" target="_blank"&gt;grep&lt;/a&gt; for. When this process starts it will look for the httpd.conf file. The web servers main configuration file. In this file you can specify which other configuration files you would like to load. What's great about Apache is that you can reload the configuration without having to stop the process.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Apache is very secure as you can specify what may be executed where on a very detailed level. Which file types are allowed to be served? What type of requests are accepted?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;pre class="code"&gt;
      Listen 80
      ServerRoot /usr/local/apache2
      DocumentRoot /usr/local/webroot

      &amp;lt;Directory "/usr/local/webroot"&amp;gt;
      order allow,deny
      allow from all
      &amp;lt;/Directory&amp;gt;

      &amp;lt;IfModule mod_ssl.c&amp;gt;
        Include conf/ssl.conf
      &amp;lt;/IfModule&amp;gt;
    &lt;/pre&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Listen is the port number on which the server should listen. The default for web browsing is port 80 and for secure browsing (https) this would be port 443. The server root is where the daemon will search for configuration files. The Documentroot is where the html (and other files) resides.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;In this directory you can specify allow or deny rules based on IP addresses. This is very important for secure and controlled HTTP server environments. In this scenario all access is allowed and nothing denied, which means it is a public website.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Lastly, the IfModule inclusion specifies which modules to load. Apache has a large library of modules, including SSL configuration (as in the example), log configurations and also native coding language support.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;For a more complete example of an httpd.conf file and further explanations please have a &lt;a href="http://www.faqs.org/docs/securing/chap29sec245.html" target="_blank"&gt;look here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;

  &lt;section&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Below the surface&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This only really scratches the surface. I have found the possibilities to be near endless. I would like to conclude with a short description of Nginx.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
  &lt;section&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Nginx&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As you an see in the survey link above, after Microsoft IIS, the most used web server is Nginx. (Pronounced Engine-X) It seems to be growing in popularity as well. Personally I wasn't really aware of the differences, but I found &lt;a href="https://anturis.com/blog/nginx-vs-apache/" target="_blank"&gt;this excellent comparison&lt;/a&gt; outlining the differences. Since we at DBC will be Ruby it is interesting to know that Ruby is one of the languages natively supported by Apache through the Ruby module; mod_ruby.
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;

  &lt;section&gt;
    &lt;h2&gt;Finally&lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have worked with Apache, but haven't touched half of its options. Apache is relatively easy to set up on a simple environment and provides flexibility for complexity. I hope you enjoyed my brief overview here and if you are interested I would encourage looking up more resources. When you want to host the awesome websites and applications you will build it could be interesting to get more familiar with this technology.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Personally I also believe that the more knowledge you have over the entire chain in which your program runs, the easier you will be able to pinpoint any problems you run which in turn helps you to solve them faster. This has been my experience with problem analysis and troubleshooting over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/article&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
